Mykhaylo Mykolaiovich Malakhov

THE BASICS

Cell phone: (530) 840-6245 Email: mykhaylo@andrews.edu

Blog: mykmal.xyz

Permanent address: 21105 Rolling Hills Rd Manton, CA 96059

Citizenship: United States Date of birth: June 27, 1998 Pronouns: he, him, his

RESEARCH INTERESTS I love all applications of mathematics and statistics, and my current research focuses on dynamical systems. I study manifold reconstruction and bifurcation theory, especially within the context of differential equation and periodic matrix models of chemical reactions, infectious diseases (both human and animal), and animal behavior.

EDUCATION

Andrews University

B.S. in Mathematics (expected May 2020)

- Minor in Computing
- Honors Thesis: Managing White-nose Syndrome in Bats: A Spatially Dynamic Modelling Approach
- Goldwater Scholar
- J. N. Andrews Honors Scholar
- 4.00 GPA

Budapest Semesters in Mathematics (Fall 2019)

I will be studying abroad through the Budapest Semesters in Mathematics program for the Fall 2019 semester.

RESEARCH EXPERIENCE

RIPS program, IPAM, UCLA (Summer 2019)

I am participating in the Research in Industrial Projects for Students (RIPS) REU/internship program at the Institute for Pure and Applied Mathematics (IPAM) at the University of California, Los Angeles (UCLA).

Advisors:

- An Do, Institute of Mathematical Sciences, Claremont Graduate University
- Robert S. Martin, In-space Propulsion Branch, Rocket Propulsion Division, Aerospace Systems Directorate, Air Force Research Laboratory
- Daniel Q. Eckhardt, In-space Propulsion Branch, Rocket Propulsion Division, Aerospace Systems Directorate, Air Force Research Laboratory

I am the Project Manager for the Air Force Research Laboratory team. Our team is working on the first attempt to employ empirical dynamic modeling techniques to study intermediate-scale dynamical systems. In particular, we are applying convergent cross mapping to simulated time series data from a continuously stirred hydrogen-oxygen tank reactor model. We plan to determine the extent to which convergent bijective maps can be constructed between shadow manifolds of various system observables across a range of reactor input perturbations and model parameter values.

SMALL Undergraduate Research Project, Williams College (Summer 2018) Advisors:

- Julie C. Blackwood, Department of Mathematics and Statistics, Williams College
- Katriona Shea, Department of Biology and Center for Infectious Disease Dynamics, The Pennsylvania State University

I was part of the mathematical ecology group, where I worked on two projects. In one project we investigated how seasonal bat dispersal could affect the success of white-nose syndrome control strategies by posing and numerically analyzing the first spatially-explicit ODE model of white-nose syndrome. The second project focused on the perspective of ecosystem federalism as applied to infectious disease management; we explored the allocation of regulatory authority between different levels of government using a two-patch SIRS-type model.

Seabird Ecology Team REU, Andrews University (Summer 2017)

Advisors:

- Shandelle M. Henson, Department of Mathematics and Department of Biology, Andrews University
- J. M. Cushing, Department of Mathematics and Interdisciplinary Program in Applied Mathematics, University of Arizona

We analyzed a 3-dimensional, nonlinear periodic matrix model of seabird behavior and population dynamics using both numerical and analytic techniques. I demonstrated the existence of backward bifurcations due to egg cannibalism and proved that egg-laying synchrony is always detrimental given short breeding seasons.

PUBLICATIONS

Junyan Duan[†], Mykhaylo M. Malakhov[†], Jordan J. Pellett[†], Ishan Phadke[†], Katriona Shea, David M. Kling, Suzanne Lenhart, James N. Sanchirico, Michael G. Neubert, and Julie C. Blackwood. *Transboundary Disease Management Under Alternative Objectives*. In preparation.

Mykhaylo M. Malakhov, Benjamin MacDonald, J. M. Cushing, and Shandelle M. Henson. A Note on Dimensionality in a Structured Seabird Population Model. In preparation.

Junyan Duan[†], Mykhaylo M. Malakhov[†], Jordan J. Pellett[†], Ishan Phadke[†], Jackson Barber, and Julie C. Blackwood. *Management Efficacy in a Spatially Dynamic Model of White-nose Syndrome*. Submitted.

Conference Presentations

Managing White-nose Syndrome in Bats: A Spatially Dynamic Modelling Approach. 2019 Honors Thesis Symposium; Andrews University; Berrien Springs, MI. (April 2019)

Modeling the impact of bat dispersal on white-nose syndrome control strategies. Mathematics Section; Michigan Academy of Science, Arts, and Letters; Alma College; Alma, MI. (March 2019)

Federalism in Epidemic Modeling: Multi-objective Management of Interconnected Populations. AMS-MAA-SIAM Special Session on Research in Mathematics by Under-

[†] Authors contributed equally to this work

graduates and Students in Post-Baccalaureate Programs; Joint Mathematics Meetings; Baltimore, MD. Jointly with Ishan Phadke. (January 2019)

Cannibalism and synchrony in a periodic matrix seabird population model. Mathematics Section; Michigan Academy of Science, Arts, and Letters; Central Michigan University; Mount Pleasant, MI. (March 2018)

Backward Bifurcations in a Periodic Matrix Model of Seabird Population Dynamics. MAA General Contributed Paper Session on Modeling and Applications; Joint Mathematics Meetings; San Diego, CA. (January 2018)

OTHER ORAL PRESENTATIONS

Application of Convergent Cross Mapping to Chemical Reactions. RIPS Midterm Presentations Session; Institute for Pure and Applied Mathematics; University of California, Los Angeles; Los Angeles, CA. Jointly with Brianna Fitzpatrick, Rebecca Lopez, and Abhishek Shivkumar. (July 2019)

SMALL Projects for a Big World: Spatial Models of Infectious Disease. eigen*Talk (undergraduate math/physics colloquium); Andrews University; Berrien Springs, MI. (November 2018)

Differential Geometry: History, Theory, and Applications. eigen*Talk (undergraduate math/physics colloquium); Andrews University; Berrien Springs, MI. Jointly with other MATH 487 Differential Geometry students. (April 2018)

Effects of Sea Surface Temperature on Seabird Behavior in the Pacific Northwest. eigen*Talk (undergraduate math/physics colloquium); Andrews University; Berrien Springs, MI. (September 2017)

Uncertainty in Mathematics: A Historical Analysis of the Validity and Rigor of Mathematical Statements. eigen*Talk (undergraduate math/physics colloquium); Andrews University; Berrien Springs, MI. Jointly with Robert C. Moore and Lukasz Krzywon. (April 2017)

POSTER PRESENTATIONS

Managing White-nose Syndrome in Bats: A Spatially Dynamic Modeling Approach. 2019 Honors Scholars and Undergraduate Research Poster Symposium; Andrews University; Berrien Springs, MI. (March 2019)

Efficacy of Control in a Spatially Dynamic Model of White-nose Syndrome. Summer Science Poster Session; Williams College; Williamstown, MA. Jointly with Ishan Phadke. (August 2018)

A Periodic Matrix Model of Seabird Behavior and Population Dynamics. 2018 Honors Scholars and Undergraduate Research Poster Symposium; Andrews University; Berrien Springs, MI. (March 2018)

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

Department of Mathematics, Andrews University

Lecturer for LATEX short course (Spring 2019)

Grader for MATH 355 Foundations of Advanced Mathematics (Spring 2018, Spring 2019)

Tutor for the Mathematics Center (Spring 2017 – Spring 2019)

Teaching Assistant for MATH 192 Calculus II (Spring 2017)

Private math tutor (Fall 2016 – Spring 2019)

HONORS AND AWARDS

National and International Awards

Member, Nu Sigma Chapter of Sigma Tau Delta: The International English Honor Society (inducted 2019)

Member, Chapter 249 of The Honor Society of Phi Kappa Phi (inducted 2019)

Barry M. Goldwater Scholarship (2018)

Member, Michigan Gamma Chapter of Pi Mu Epsilon: The National Mathematics Honor Society (inducted 2018)

Associate Member, Andrews-Whirlpool Chapter of Sigma Xi: The Scientific Research Honor Society (inducted 2017)

Andrews University Awards

Dean's List (every semester)

J. N. Andrews Honors Scholar (admitted into the program 2016)

Full Tuition ACT/SAT Scholarship (awarded 2016 for four years)

Andrews University Department of Mathematics Awards

Award for Excellence in Probability Theory with Statistical Applications (2019)

Award for Excellence in Complex Analysis (2019)

Award for Excellence in Applied Mathematics (2019)

Award for Excellence in Abstract Algebra (2019)

Award for Excellence in Geometry (2019)

Harold T. Jones Scholarship (2018) for highest overall excellence in mathematics

Louis Ulloth Scholarship (2018) for most significant leadership contributions

Award for Excellence in Differential Equations (2018)

Award for Excellence in Mathematical Modeling in Biology (2018)

Award for Excellence in Calculus III (2018)

Putnam Competition team member (2017 and 2018) and highest scorer (2018)

Award for Excellence in Foundations of Advanced Mathematics (2017)

Award for Excellence in Calculus II (2017)

Award for Excellence in Calculus I (2017)

SERVICE AND OUTREACH

President, Michigan Gamma Chapter, Pi Mu Epsilon (2018 – present)

I organize π Day festivities, game nights, and other fun activities. After one year of service I was reelected for a second term.

Vice President, AU Chapter, Engineers Without Borders (2018 – 2019)

I oversaw all club administration and functions, as well as the initial phases of a \$60,000+ solar energy project in Madagascar. The summer of 2018 I traveled to Madagascar to conduct the assessment phase of our project.

Mathematics President, eigen*: the AU math/physics club (2017 – 2018)

I planned math-related colloquia and events and invited guest speakers. I also organized the first-ever Putnam Competition team and preparation course at AU.

Treasurer, AU Chapter, Engineers Without Borders (2017 – 2018)

I oversaw all club and project finances, grant applications, and fundraising. During my time as Treasurer we raised about \$20,000.

Founding Student Leader, codeShack: Google igniteCS @ AU (2016-2017) I helped start a computer science education program at the local elementary school and wrote a successful application for Google igniteCS funding.

Relevant Skills Human Languages:

English (native), Russian (native), Spanish (intermediate), Ukrainian (beginner), Hungarian (beginner)

Programming Languages (by descending level of proficiency): MATLAB, LATEX, Java, Python, C++, Processing

Software:

Microsoft Office, Linux, GitHub, Scientific WorkPlace, Cantera